José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

A research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013-Now	Doctor	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon"	
2010–2012	Master in Computer Science "A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain of this work generated a product still in u and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http	se by the Brazilian National Education
2005–2010	Bachelor in Computer Engineer "A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Prot	Federal University of Pará, Brazil ocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

Experience

2016

Technical Adviser

	tation Center For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware requested by the <i>Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice</i> .	
2016	To the Yokohama National University For the production of a report about "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks requested by the <i>Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications</i> .	

To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

Assistant Professor

University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses:

Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016	Product Design to Online Business (course) Audience: bachelor students of industrial engine technology.	University of Twente, The Netherlands neering and business information
2015	Network Security (course)	University of Twente, The Netherlands
	Audience: master and bachelor students of o	computer science, electrical en-
	gineer, and telematics from the University of T	wente, 3TU cyber security, and

2015 **Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor)**University of Twente, The Netherlands
Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research
Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Universität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

members of ICT labs.

Software Developer

2015–Now **Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)**

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP)

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application sponsored by Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian

power utility (Eletrobrás). Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Student Supervisor

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications(2011)

Awards

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch'	(1 st Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 rd Place)		CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award	Autonomous Infrastructure,	Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Bra	zilian Symposium on Comp	uter Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 rd Place)	Computer En	gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

Communication Skills

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (see in: http://www.slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	Oral Presentation	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	Oral Presentation t	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	Oral Presentation	at the 31 th and 36 th IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

Scientific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research

Publications